One hot October morning,
في صباح حار من أكتوبر
I got off the all-night train
ترجلت من القطار الليلي
in Mandalay,
في ماندالاي
the old royal capital of Burma,
العاصمة القديمة الملكية لبورما
now Myanmar.
والتي تُعرف الآن بـ ميانمار
And out on the street, I ran into a group of rough men
وفي الشارع، صادفت جماعة من الرجال المشردين
standing beside their bicycle rickshaws.
يقفون بجانب دراجة الريكاشة (عربة هندية)
And one of them came up
اقترب أحدهم مني
and offered to show me around.
واقترح علي أن يٌريني المكان
The price he quoted was outrageous.
السعر الذي طلبه كان مدهشاً للغاية
It was less than I would pay for a bar of chocolate at home.
كان أقل من ذلك الذي يمكن أن أدفعه مقابل لوح من الشكلاطة في المنزل
So I clambered into his trishaw,
لذا ركبت في عربته
and he began pedaling us slowly between palaces and pagodas.
وبدأنا في المشي ببطىء بين القصور والمعابد البوذية
And as he did, he told me how he had come to the city from his village.
وخلال مرورنا بها، أخبرني عن كيفية مغادرته لقريته ومجيئه إلى المدينة
He'd earned a degree in mathematics.
نال شهادةً جامعيةً في الرياضيات
His dream was to be a teacher.
وكان يحلم بأن يصبح معلّماً
But of course, life is hard under a military dictatorship,
ولكن بالطبع، الحياة قاسية في ظل نظام دكتاتوري عسكري
and so for now, this was the only way he could make a living.
وفي ذلك الحين، كانت هذه العربة هي مصدر رزقه الوحيد
Many nights, he told me, he actually slept in his trishaw
أخبرني في كثير من الليالي أنه كان ينام في عربته
so he could catch the first visitors off the all-night train.
لكي يضمن مصادفة أول الزائرين المترجلين من القطار الليلي
And very soon, we found that in certain ways,
وفي وقت قريب، وجدنا أنه، وبطرق معينة
we had so much in common --
لدينا الكثير من القواسم المشتركة
we were both in our 20s,
كلانا كان في العشرينات من عمره،
we were both fascinated by foreign cultures --
وكلانا كان ولوعاً بالثقافات الأجنبية
that he invited me home.
لذا، دعاني لمنزله
So we turned off the wide, crowded streets,
فتركنا الشوارع العريضة المزدحمة،
and we began bumping down rough, wild alleyways.
وبدأنا بالارتطام إلى الأسفل، في أزقة وعرة قاسية
There were broken shacks all around.
كانت توجد عدة أكواخ محطمة من حولنا،
I really lost the sense of where I was,
وفقدت الإدراك بما حولي حينها،
and I realized that anything could happen to me now.
وأدركت أن أي شيء ممكن أن يحدث لي الآن
I could get mugged or drugged
يمكن أن أٌسرق أو يتم تخدري،
or something worse.
أو شيء أسوأ من ذلك،
Nobody would know.
لن يعلم أحد بذلك.
Finally, he stopped and led me into a hut,
وفي النهاية، توقف وقادني إلى داخل كوخ ما
which consisted of just one tiny room.
والذي كان عبارة عن غرفة صغيرة واحدة
And then he leaned down,
وبعدها انحنى
and reached under his bed.
وجلب شيئا من تحت السرير
And something in me froze.
فتجمد شيء ما في،
I waited to see what he would pull out.
انتظرت ما الذي سيجلبه من هناك،
And finally he extracted a box.
وأخيرا أحضر صندوقاً
Inside it was every single letter he had ever received
كان بداخله كل الرسائل التي تلقاها في حياته،
from visitors from abroad,
من الزائرين الذين أتو من الخارج
and on some of them he had pasted
وعلى بعض منها، ألصق
little black-and-white worn snapshots
لقطات مهترئة، باللون الأبيض والاسود
of his new foreign friends.
لأصدقائه الأجانب الجدد
So when we said goodbye that night,
وعندما ودّعني تلك الليلة
I realized he had also shown me
أدركت الشيء الذي أراني إياه
the secret point of travel,
الهدف المهم من اللسفر:
which is to take a plunge,
وهو أن تغامر وتندفع
to go inwardly as well as outwardly
أن تذهب داخلياً وخارجياً
to places you would never go otherwise,
إلى أماكن لم تكن ستذهب إليها أبداً
to venture into uncertainty,
للمغامرة في المجهول
ambiguity,
الغموض
even fear.
وحتى الخوف
At home, it's dangerously easy
في الموطن الأصلي، إنه لمن السهل - وبشكل خطير -
to assume we're on top of things.
أن نظن بأننا نملك بزمام الأمور
Out in the world, you are reminded every moment that you're not,
في العالم الخارجي، تُذكّر في كل لحظة أنك لا تملك زمام الأمور
and you can't get to the bottom of things, either.
بل لا يمكنك حتى الوصول إلى حقيقة الأشياء
Everywhere, "People wish to be settled,"
في كل مكان، "ينشد الناس الاستقرار"
Ralph Waldo Emerson reminded us,
يُذكّرنا رالف واردو إيميرسون:
"but only insofar as we are unsettled
"بقدر عدم استقرارنا
is there any hope for us."
بقدر ما يكون هناك أمل"
At this conference, we've been lucky enough
في هذا المؤتمر، كنا محظوظين كفايةً
to hear some exhilarating new ideas and discoveries
لسماع بعض الأفكار المنعشة والاكتشافات
and, really, about all the ways
والحديث عن كل الطرق التي
in which knowledge is being pushed excitingly forwards.
من خلالها يتم الدفع بالمعرفة إلى الأمام وبطريقة حماسية
But at some point, knowledge gives out.
ولكن في وقت ما، تنضب المعرفة وتنفذ
And that is the moment
وتلك هي اللحظة
when your life is truly decided:
التي يتم فيها تقرير مسار حياتك فعلاً
you fall in love;
تقع في الحب
you lose a friend;
تفقد صديقاً
the lights go out.
يختفي الضوء
And it's then, when you're lost or uneasy or carried out of yourself,
وعندها - عندما تشعر بأنك ضائع، أو مضطرب، أو غير قادر على التعرف على نفسك -
that you find out who you are.
تدرك من أنت
I don't believe that ignorance is bliss.
لا أؤمن بأن الجهل هو شيء جيد
Science has unquestionably made our lives
تمكن العلم بلا شك من جعل حياتنا
brighter and longer and healthier.
أكثر نوراً، وأطول، وصحية أكثر
And I am forever grateful to the teachers who showed me the laws of physics
وأنا ممتن جداً للمعلمين الذين علموني قواعد الفيزياء
and pointed out that three times three makes nine.
وأخبروني بأن ناتج 3 ضرب 3 هو 9
I can count that out on my fingers
أستطيع حساب ذلك باستخدام أصابعي
any time of night or day.
في أي وقت، ليلاً أو نهاراً
But when a mathematician tells me
ولكن عندما تخبرني الرياضيات بأن
that minus three times minus three makes nine,
ناقص 3 ضرب ناقص 3 هو 9
that's a kind of logic that almost feels like trust.
هذا هو المنطق الذي يبدو أنه يستند على الثقة
The opposite of knowledge, in other words, isn't always ignorance.
ذلك يعني أن عكس المعرفة لا يكون الجهل دائماً
It can be wonder.
قد يكون الاندهاش
Or mystery.
أو الغموض
Possibility.
الاحتمال
And in my life, I've found it's the things I don't know
وفي حياتي، وجدت أن الأشياء التي لا أعرفها
that have lifted me up and pushed me forwards
هي التي رفعتني إلى الأعلى وأعظتني دفعة إلى الأمام
much more than the things I do know.
أكثر من الأشياء التي أعرفها
It's also the things I don't know
كما أنها الأشياء التي لا أعرفها
that have often brought me closer to everybody around me.
هي التي غالباً ما جعلتني أقرب إلى كل من حولي
For eight straight Novembers, recently,
مؤخراً، وفي كل شهر نوفمبر على مر 8 سنوات
I traveled every year across Japan with the Dalai Lama.
كنت أسافر في كل سنة في أرجاء اليابان، بصحبة الداي لاما
And the one thing he said every day
والشيء الوحيد الذي كان يردده كل يوم
that most seemed to give people reassurance and confidence
والذي كان يبدو أنه يمنح الناس الطمأنينة والثقة
was, "I don't know."
كان: "لا أعلم"
"What's going to happen to Tibet?"
"ماذا سيحدث للتبت؟"
"When are we ever going to get world peace?"
"متى سنستطيع تحقيق السلام غي العالم؟"
"What's the best way to raise children?"
"ما هي أفضل طريقة لتربية الأطفال؟"
"Frankly," says this very wise man,
يقول الرجل الشديد الحكمة: "بصراحة"
"I don't know."
"لا أعرف"
The Nobel Prize-winning economist Daniel Kahneman
عالم الاقتصاد الحائز على جائزة نوبل - دانييل كاهىيمان -
has spent more than 60 years now researching human behavior,
قد قضى أكثر من ستين عاماً حتى الآن في دراسة سلوك الإنسان
and his conclusion is
والخلاصة التي توصل لها هي
that we are always much more confident of what we think we know
أننا دائماً لدينا ثقة أكثر حيال الأشياء التي نظن أننا نعرفها
than we should be.
أكثر من الثقة التي يجب أن نكون عليها
We have, as he memorably puts it,
وفي عبارة مأثورة له، يقول: "لدينا
an "unlimited ability to ignore our ignorance."
"قدرة هائلة لتجاهل جهلنا"
We know -- quote, unquote -- our team is going to win this weekend,
نعلم أن فريقنا سيربح في عطلة نهاية الاسبوع هذه
and we only remember that knowledge
ونتذكر فقط هذه المعلومة
on the rare occasions when we're right.
في المرات التي نكون فيها على صواب
Most of the time, we're in the dark.
في أغلب الوقت، نكون قابعين في الظلام
And that's where real intimacy lies.
وهناك توجد الألفة الحقيقية
Do you know what your lover is going to do tomorrow?
هل تعرف مالذي سيفعله حبيبك غداً؟
Do you want to know?
أهل تريد أن تعرف؟
The parents of us all, as some people call them,
آباؤنا جميعنا، كما يسميهم البعض
Adam and Eve,
آدم وحواء
could never die, so long as they were eating from the tree of life.
لم يتمكنوا من الموت أبداً لطالما كانوا يأكلون من شجرة الحياة
But the minute they began nibbling
ولكن اللحظة التي بدؤوا فيها بأخذ بعض القضمات
from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
من شجرة المعرفة (شجرة الخير والشر)
they fell from their innocence.
فقدوا براءتهم
They grew embarrassed and fretful,
أصبحوا محرجين وقلقين
self-conscious.
وواعين بأنفسهم
And they learned, a little too late, perhaps,
وقد تعلموا، ربما في وقت متأخر
that there are certainly some things that we need to know,
أن هناك بعض الأشياء التي علينا فعلاً أن نعلمها
but there are many, many more that are better left unexplored.
ولكن هناك الكثير والكثير من الأشياء التي من الأفضل ألا نستكشفها
Now, when I was a kid,
عندما كنت صغيراً
I knew it all, of course.
كنت أعرف كل شيء طبعاً
I had been spending 20 years in classrooms collecting facts,
كنت قد أمضيت عشرين سنة في الصفوف أجمّع الحقائق
and I was actually in the information business,
وكنت متخصصا في مجا المعلومات التجارية
writing articles for Time Magazine.
أكتب المقالات لمجلة الـ "تايم"
And I took my first real trip to Japan for two-and-a-half weeks,
وقمت برحلتي الأولى لليابان لمدة أسبوعين ونصف
and I came back with a 40-page essay
وعدت ومعي مقال طوله 40 صفحة
explaining every last detail about Japan's temples,
يشرح أحدث التفاصيل عن المعابد الموجودة في اليونان
its fashions, its baseball games,
طرازها،ولعبة البيسبول الموجودة بها
its soul.
روحها
But underneath all that,
ولكن وراء هذا كله
something that I couldn't understand
شيء ما لم أكن قادراً على فهمه
so moved me for reasons I couldn't explain to you yet,
وأثر في بشكل كبير لأسباب لا أستطيع شرحها لكم بعد
that I decided to go and live in Japan.
لدرجة أنني قررت الانتقال إلى اليابان والعيش فيها
And now that I've been there for 28 years,
والآن، وبعد أن أمضيت فيها 28 سنة
I really couldn't tell you very much at all
لا أستطيع أن أخبركم أي شيء تقريباً
about my adopted home.
عن موطني الذي تبنيّته
Which is wonderful,
وهو أمر رائع
because it means every day I'm making some new discovery,
لأن ذلك يعني أنني أقوم باكتشافات جديدة في كل يوم
and in the process,
وفي خلال هذه العملية
looking around the corner and seeing the hundred thousand things
أبحث من حولي، وأرى مئات الآلاف من الأشياء
I'll never know.
التي لن أعرفها أبداً
Knowledge is a priceless gift.
المعرفة هدية لا تقدر بثمن
But the illusion of knowledge can be more dangerous than ignorance.
ولكن وهم المعرفة يمكن أن يكون أخطر من الجهل
Thinking that you know your lover
الظن بأنك تعرف حبيبك
or your enemy
أو عدوّك
can be more treacherous
يمكن أن شعوراً أكثر غدراً
than acknowledging you'll never know them.
من اعترافك بأنك لن تعرفهم أبداً
Every morning in Japan, as the sun is flooding into our little apartment,
كل صباح في اليابان، وعند تدفق أشعة الشمس إلى شقتنا الصغيرة
I take great pains not to consult the weather forecast,
أرغم نفسي كارهاً على عدم الاطلاع على أحوال الطقس
because if I do,
لأنني إن اطلعت عليها
my mind will be overclouded, distracted,
فسيبقى ذهني ملبّداً بالغيوم، مشتتاً
even when the day is bright.
حتى وإن كان الطقس مشمساً
I've been a full-time writer now for 34 years.
أمضيت 34 سنة من عمري أعمل ككاتب بدوام كامل
And the one thing that I have learned
والشيء الوحيد الذي تعلمته
is that transformation comes when I'm not in charge,
هو أن التغيير يحدث عندما لا أكون أنا من يمسك بزمام الأمور
when I don't know what's coming next,
عندما لا أعرف ماذا سيحدث لاحقاً
when I can't assume I am bigger than everything around me.
عندما لا يمكنني أن أفترض أنني أكبر من كل شيء حولي
And the same is true in love
والشيء ذاته ينطبق على الحب
or in moments of crisis.
أو في وقت الأزمات
Suddenly, we're back in that trishaw again
فجأةً، نجد أنفسنا قد عدنا إلى مرحلة "العربة الهندية" مجدداً
and we're bumping off the broad, well-lit streets;
ونرتطم بالأرض، نمضي في شوارع مُضاءة جيداً
and we're reminded, really, of the first law of travel
فيتم تذكيرنا، حقيقةً، بأن أول قواعد السفر
and, therefore, of life:
وبالتالي، أول قواعد الحياة
you're only as strong as your readiness to surrender.
أنت تكون قوياً فقط عندما تكون جاهزاً للتسليم والتخلي
In the end, perhaps,
في النهاية، ربما
being human
أن تكون إنساناً
is much more important
أهم بكثير
than being fully in the know.
من أن تكون على علم بكل شيء
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)